I've been multiplying matrices already,
하지만 이제 행렬 곱셈의 규칙에 대해 논의할 때가 확실히 된 것 같아요.
but certainly time for me to discuss the rules for matrix multiplication.
흥미로운 점은 행렬 곱셈을 할 수 있는 여러 가지 방법이 있다는 거예요.
And the interesting part is the many ways you can do it,
그리고 그 방법들은 모두 같은 결과를 주고, 모두 중요해요. 그래서 행렬 곱셈, 그리고 그 다음엔 역행렬(inverses)에 대해 이야기할게요.
and they all give the same answer. And they're all important. So matrix multiplication, and then, come inverses.
그래서 우리는 행렬의 역행렬(inverse)에 대해 언급했었죠. 그건 아주 중요한 주제예요.
So we mentioned the inverse of a matrix. That's a big deal.
역행렬에 대해 할 이야기가 많고, 그걸 어떻게 찾는지에 대해서도요. 자, 그럼 두 행렬을 어떻게 곱하는지부터 시작할게요.
Lots to do about inverses and how to find them. Okay, so I'll begin with how to multiply two matrices.
첫 번째 방법, 좋아요. 제가 행렬 A가 있다고 가정하고
First way, okay, so suppose I have a matrix A multiplying
그 행렬 A가 행렬 B를 곱해서 — 결과를 얻는다고 해볼게요 —
a matrix B and -- giving me a result --
음, 그 결과를 C라고 부를 수 있겠네요. A 곱하기 B예요. 좋아요.
well, I could call it C. A times B. Okay.
자, 그럼 이 항목에 대한 규칙을 간단히 검토해 볼게요.
So, let me just review the rule for this entry.
그건 i번째 행과 j번째 열에 있는 항목이에요. 그래서 그게 i j 항목이죠.
That's the entry in row i and column j. So that's the i j entry.
바로 여기 C i j가 있어요. 우리는 항상 행 번호를 먼저 쓰고 그 다음에 열 번호를 써요.
Right there is C i j. We always write the row number and then the column number.
그래서 저는 — 아마도 — C 3 4를 예로 들어볼게요, 구체적으로 만들기 위해서요.
So I might -- I might -- maybe I take it C 3 4, just to make it specific.
그래서 i j 대신에 숫자를 써볼게요. C 3 4예요. 그럼 이 3 4 항목은 어디서 오는 걸까요?
So instead of i j, let me use numbers. C 3 4. So where does that come from, the three four entry?
그건 여기 3번째 행, 3번째 행과 4번째 열에서 오는 거예요.
It comes from row three, here, row three and column four,
아시다시피 4번째 열이죠. 그럼 그 공식을 적어볼까요, 아니면 우리가 공식을 적어볼까요?
as you know. Column four. And can I just write down, or can we write down the formula for it?
만약 우리가 전체 행과 전체 열을 본다면, 제가 간단히 말하는 빠른 방법은 A의 3번째 행이에요 —
If we look at the whole row and the whole column, the quick way for me to say it is row three of A --
내적(dot product)을 위해 점을 사용할 수도 있겠네요. 사실 저는 자주 그렇게 하진 않을 거예요. B의 4번째 열과요.
I could use a dot for dot product. I won't often use that, actually. Dot column four of B.
하지만 이건 우리가 약간의 행렬 표기법을 사용할 기회를 주네요.
But this gives us a chance to just, like, use a little matrix notation.
항목들이 뭐예요? 3번째 행의 첫 번째 항목이 뭐죠?
What are the entries? What's this first entry in row three?
거기 있는 숫자는... A예요, 그래서 두 가지 인덱스가 있고 그게 뭐예요?
That number that's sitting right there is... A, so it's got two indices and what are they?
3 1이죠. 그래서 거기에 a 3 1이 있어요. 자, 그럼 4번째 열 맨 위에 있는 첫 번째 숫자는 뭐예요?
3 1. So there's an a 3 1 there. Now what's the first guy at the top of column four?
거기 위에 있는 건 뭐죠? B 1 4예요, 맞죠.
So what's sitting up there? B 1 4, right.
그래서 이 내적은 A 3 1 곱하기 B 1 4로 시작해요.
So that this dot product starts with A 3 1 times B 1 4.
그리고 다음은 뭐죠 — 그래서 제가 이 합을 누적하고 있는 것처럼, 그 다음은 A 3 2, 두 번째 열,
And then what's the next -- so this is like I'm accumulating this sum, then comes the next guy, A 3 2, second column,
곱하기 B 2 4, 두 번째 행이에요. 그래서 B A 3 2, B 2 4 이렇게 계속되죠.
times B 2 4, second row. So it's b A 3 2, B 2 4 and so on.
인덱스로 연습하는 거예요. 오, 심지어 합계 공식으로 연습해 볼게요.
Just practice with indices. Oh, let me even practice with a summation formula.
그래서 이건 — 이 강의의 대부분에서 저는 전체 벡터를 사용해요.
So this is -- most of the course, I use whole vectors.
저는 아주 드물게 이런 특정 항목의 세부 사항까지 들어가지만, 여기선 그걸 해야겠네요.
I very seldom, get down to the details of these particular entries, but here we'd better do it.
그래서 이건 일종의 합이에요, 맞죠? 3번째 행, K번째 열에 있는 것들과
So it's some kind of a sum, right? Of things in row three, column K shall I say?
K번째 행, 4번째 열에 있는 것들의 곱이에요.
Times things in row K, column four.
여기서 보이는 게 그거라는 걸 아시겠죠? 여기 K가 1이고, 여기 K가 2이고, 계속해서 —
Do you see that that's what we're seeing here? This is K is one, here K is two, on along --
그래서 합은 행을 따라가고 열을 따라 내려가면서, 1부터 N까지 간다고 해볼게요.
so the sum goes all the way along the row and down the column, say, one to N.
그래서 그게 C 3 4 항목이 어떻게 생겼는지예요. A 3 K와 B K 4의 합이에요.
So that's what the C three four entry looks like. A sum of a three K b K four.
이걸 하는 데 약간의 연습이 필요해요. 좋아요. 그리고 — 음, 아마 제가 말해야 할 건 —
Just takes a little practice to do that. Okay. And -- well, maybe I should say --
우리가 언제 이 행렬들을 곱할 수 있는 걸까요? 이 행렬들의 모양은 어떤가요?
when are we allowed to multiply these matrices? What are the shapes of these things?
모양은 — 만약 우리가 정사각 행렬이 아니어도 된다고 한다면요.
The shapes are -- if we allow them to be not necessarily square matrices.
만약 정사각 행렬이라면, 크기가 같아야 해요. 직사각 행렬이라면 크기가 같지 않아요.
If they're square, they've got to be the same size. If they're rectangular, they're not the same size.
직사각 행렬이라면, 이건 — 음, 저는 항상 A를 m행 n열(m by n)로 생각해요.
If they're rectangular, this might be -- well, I always think of A as m by n.
m개의 행, n개의 열이죠. 그래서 그 합은 n까지 가요.
m rows, n columns. So that sum goes to n.
자, 그럼 요점이 뭐냐 — B는 몇 개의 행을 가져야 하나요?
Now what's the point -- how many rows does B have to have?
n이요. B의 행의 수, 우리가 내려오면서 만나는 숫자의 개수는 가로로 있는 숫자의 개수와
n. The number of rows in B, the number of guys that we meet coming down has to match the number of ones
맞아야 해요. 그래서 B는 n행 뭔가 열이어야 해요.
across. So B will have to be n by something.
아무거나요. P라고 하죠. 그래서 여기 열의 수는 여기 행의 수와
Whatever. P. So the number of columns here has to match the number of rows
맞아야 하고, 그럼 결과는 뭐죠? 결과의 모양은 뭐예요? C, 출력의 모양은 뭐죠?
there, and then what's the result? What's the shape of the result? What's the shape of C, the output?
음, 여기 같은 m개의 행이 있어요 — m개의 행이죠.
Well, it's got these same m rows -- it's got m rows.
그리고 열은 몇 개죠? P예요. m행 P열(m by P)이죠. 좋아요.
And how many columns? P. m by P. Okay.
그래서 거기에 m 곱하기 P개의 작은 숫자들, 항목들이 있고, 각각이 그렇게 생겼어요.
So there are m times P little numbers in there, entries, and each one, looks like that.
좋아요. 그게 표준 규칙이에요. 그게 사람들이 행렬을 곱한다고 생각하는 방식이에요.
Okay. So that's the standard rule. That's the way people think of multiplying matrices.
저도 그렇게 해요.
I do it too.
하지만 저는 같은 계산을 다른 방식으로 보는 방법에 대해 이야기하고 싶어요.
But I want to talk about other ways to look at that same calculation,
전체 열과 전체 행을 보는 거예요.
looking at whole columns and whole rows.
좋아요. 그럼 다시 A B C를 해볼까요? 다시 A B가 C가 되는 거예요?
Okay. So can I do A B C again? A B equaling C again?
하지만 이제, 저에게 말해 주세요...
But now, tell me about...
여기 위에 올려놓겠습니다. 자, 다시 A가 있고, B를 곱해서 C를 만들어요.
I'll put it up here. So here goes A, again, times B producing C.
그리고 다시, 이건 m행 n열(m by n)이고, 이건 n행 P열(n by P)이고, 이건 m행 P열(m by P)이에요. 좋아요.
And again, this is m by n. This is n by P and this is m by P. Okay.
이제 저는 전체 열을 보고 싶어요. 이 열들을 보고 싶어요 —
Now I want to look at whole columns. I want to look at the columns of --
여기 행렬을 곱하는 두 번째 방법이 있어요. 왜냐하면 저는 이미 아는 걸 바탕으로 쌓아갈 거니까요.
here's the second way to multiply matrices. Because I'm going to build on what I know already.
행렬을 열로 곱하는 법을 어떻게 아냐고요? 저는 이 행렬을 저 열로 곱하는 법을 알아요.
How do I multiply a matrix by a column? I know how to multiply this matrix by that column.
그걸 1번 열이라고 불러볼까요?
Shall I call that column one?
그건 답의 1번 열을 알려줘요.
That tells me column one of the answer.
행렬 곱하기 첫 번째 열은 그 첫 번째 열이에요. 왜냐하면 이 부분은 답의 그 부분에 전혀 들어가지 않았으니까요.
The matrix times the first column is that first column. Because none of this stuff entered
행렬 곱하기 두 번째 열은 답의 두 번째 열이에요.
that part of the answer. The matrix times the second column is the second column of the answer.
제가 무슨 말을 하는지 아시겠죠? 행렬을 곱한다고 생각할 수 있다는 거예요.
Do you see what I'm saying? That I could think of multiplying a matrix
벡터로요. 그건 제가 이미 어떻게 하는지 아는 거고, 저는 그냥 P개의 열이 나란히 있다고 생각할 수 있어요.
by a vector, which I already knew how to do, and I can think of just P columns sitting side by side,
서로 옆에 붙어 있는 것처럼요. 그리고 저는 A를 그 각각의 열에 곱해요.
just like resting next to each other. And I multiply A times each one of those.
그러면 답의 P개의 열을 얻어요. 이게 — 꽤 멋지죠.
And I get the P columns of the answer. Do you see this as -- this is quite nice,
생각할 수 있다는 게, 좋아요, 행렬 곱셈이 그렇게 작동해서
to be able to think, okay, matrix multiplication works
제가 여러 개의 열을 가지고 있다고 생각하고, A로 곱해서 답의 열들을 얻을 수 있다는 거예요.
so that I can just think of having several columns, multiplying by A and getting the columns of the answer.
그래서, 여기 1번 열이 있어요. 그걸 1번 열이라고 불러볼까요?
So, like, here's column one shall I call that column one?
그리고 거기에 들어가는 건 A 곱하기 1번 열이에요.
And what's going in there is A times column one.
좋아요. 그게 한 번에 열 단위로 보는 그림이에요. 그럼 그게 저에게 뭐를 말해 주나요?
Okay. So that's the picture a column at a time. So what does that tell me?
이 열들이 저에게 뭘 말해 주나요? C의 이 열들은 조합(combination)이에요.
What does that tell me about these columns? These columns of C are combinations,
왜냐하면 우리는 그걸 전에 봤으니까요, A의 열들의 조합이죠.
because we've seen that before, of columns of A.
이 각각은 A 곱하기 이거에서 오고, A 곱하기 벡터는 A의 열들의 조합이에요.
Every one of these comes from A times this, and A times a vector is a combination
그리고 그게 말이 되죠. 왜냐하면 A의 열들은 길이가 m이고
of the columns of A. And it makes sense, because the columns of A have length m
C의 열들도 길이가 m이니까요. 그리고 C의 모든 열은 A의 열들의 어떤 조합이에요.
and the columns of C have length m. And every column of C is some combination
그리고 여기 있는 이 숫자들이 그게 어떤 조합인지 저에게 말해 줘요.
of the columns of A. And it's these numbers in here that tell me what combination it is.
그거 보이세요? 그 답, C에서, 저는 이 열들의
Do you see that? That in that answer, C, I'm seeing stuff that's
조합인 것들을 보고 있어요. 자, 이제 제가 행 단위로 본다고 가정해 볼게요. 그럼 이제 두 가지 방법이 됐네요.
combinations of these columns. Now, suppose I look at it -- that's two ways now.
세 번째 방법은 행 단위로 보는 거예요. 그럼 이제 행으로 바꿔볼게요.
The third way is look at it by rows. So now let me change to rows.
좋아요. 그럼 이제 저는 A의 행을 생각할 수 있어요 —
Okay. So now I can think of a row of A --
A의 행이 여기 있는 이 모든 행들을 곱해서 결과물의 행을 만들어내요.
a row of A multiplying all these rows here and producing a row
그래서 이 행은 이 행들의 조합을 취해서 그게 답이에요.
of the product. So this row takes a combination of these rows
그럼 C의 이 행들은 뭐의 조합이죠?
and that's the answer. So these rows of C are combinations of what?
저에게 그걸 어떻게 마무리할지 말해 주세요. C의 행들, 제가 B 행렬을 가지고 있을 때, 그건 그 행들을 가지고 있고
Tell me how to finish that. The rows of C, when I have a matrix B, it's got its rows
A로 곱하면, 그게 뭐를 하나요? 행들을 섞어요.
and I multiply by A, and what does that do? It mixes the rows up.
B의 행들의 조합을 만들어내요, 감사합니다.
It creates combinations of the rows of B, thanks.
B의 행들이요. 그게 제가 보고 싶었던 거예요. 이 답에서 —
Rows of B. That's what I wanted to see, that this answer --
저는 조각들이 어디서 오는지 볼 수 있어요. 답의 행들은 이 행들의 조합으로 오고 있어요.
I can see where the pieces are coming from. The rows in the answer are coming as combinations of these
답의 열들은 저 열들의 조합으로 오고 있어요.
rows. The columns in the answer are coming as combinations of those
그래서 그게 세 가지 방법이에요. 이제 여러분이 말할 수 있겠죠, 좋아, 그럼 네 번째 방법은 뭐예요?
columns. And so that's three ways. Now you can say, okay, what's the fourth way?
네 번째 방법 — 그래서 이제 우리는 일반적인 방법,
The fourth way -- so that's -- now we've got, like, the regular way,
열 방법, 행 방법 그리고 —
the column way, the row way and --
뭐가 남았죠? 제가 할 수 있는 건 —
what's left? The one that I can --
음, 한 가지 방법은 열 곱하기 행이에요.
well, one way is columns times rows.
만약 제가 — 그래서 이건 행 곱하기 열이었고, 그건 숫자를 줬어요.
What happens if I multiply -- So this was row times column, it gave a number.
좋아요. 이제 저는 여러분에게 열 곱하기 행에 대해 묻고 싶어요. 제가 A의 열을 B의 행으로 곱하면,
Okay. Now I want to ask you about column times row. If I multiply a column of A times a row of B,
어떤 모양이 되는 걸까요? 그래서 제가 열을 행으로 곱하면,
what shape I ending up with? So if I take a column times a row,
그건 확실히 행을 열로 곱하는 것과 다르죠. 그럼 A의 열의 모양은 뭐예요?
that's definitely different from taking a row times a column. So a column of A was -- what's the shape of a column of A?
m행 1열(m by one)이죠. A의 열은 열이에요.
m by one. A column of A is a column.
m개의 항목이 있고 한 개의 열이죠. 그럼 B의 행은 뭐예요?
It's got m entries and one column. And what's a row of B?
1행 P열이죠.
It's got one row and P columns.
그래서 제가 열을 행으로 곱하면 어떤 모양을 얻나요?
So what's the shape -- what do I get if I multiply a column by a row?
큰 행렬을 얻어요. 전체 크기의 행렬을 얻죠. 제가 열을 행으로 곱하면 —
I get a big matrix. I get a full-sized matrix. If I multiply a column by a row --
하나만 해볼까요? 2 3 4라는 열을 1 6이라는 행으로 곱해볼게요.
should we just do one? Let me take the column two three four times the row one six.
그 곱은 —
That product there --
제 말은, 제가 그냥 행렬 곱셈의 규칙을 따를 때, 그 규칙들은 그냥 —
I mean, when I'm just following the rules of matrix multiplication, those rules are just looking like --
좀 작게 보이네요, 왜냐하면 여기 행들이
kind of petite, kind of small, because the rows here
너무 짧고 거기 열들도 너무 짧지만, 길이는 같아요, 한 개의 항목이죠.
are so short and the columns there are so short, but they're the same length, one entry.
그럼 답이 뭐예요? 제가 2 3 4를 1 6으로 곱하면 답이 뭐죠, 연습으로요?
So what's the answer? What's the answer if I do two three four times one six, just
음, 답의 첫 번째 행은 뭐예요?
for practice? Well, what's the first row of the answer?
2 12예요. 그리고 답의 두 번째 행은 3 18이에요.
Two twelve. And the second row of the answer is three eighteen.
그리고 답의 세 번째 행은 4 24예요.
And the third row of the answer is four twenty four.
그건 아주 특별한 행렬이에요, 거기요.
That's a very special matrix, there.
아주 특별한 행렬이죠. 그 행렬의 열들에 대해 뭐라고 말할 수 있나요?
Very special matrix. What can you tell me about its columns, the columns of that matrix?
그건 이 녀석의 배수(multiple)이죠, 맞죠? 그 하나의 배수예요.
They're multiples of this guy, right? They're multiples of that one.
그건 우리 규칙을 따르는 거예요. 우리는 답의 열들이 조합이라고 했지만, 한 녀석의 조합을 취하면,
Which follows our rule. We said that the columns of the answer were combinations, but there's only -- to take a combination of one guy,
그건 그냥 배수일 뿐이에요. 답의 행들은요, 이 세 개의 행에 대해 뭐라고 말할 수 있나요?
it's just a multiple. The rows of the answer, what can you tell me about those three rows?
그건 모두 이 행의 배수예요.
They're all multiples of this row.
모두 1 6의 배수예요, 우리가 예상했던 대로죠. 하지만 저는 전체 크기의 행렬을 얻고 있어요.
They're all multiples of one six, as we expected. But I'm getting a full-sized matrix.
그리고 이제, 이 생각을 완성하기 위해, 제가 —
And now, just to complete this thought, if I have --
네 번째 방법을 적어볼게요.
let me write down the fourth way.
A B는 A의 열들과 B의 행들의 합이에요.
A B is a sum of columns of A times rows of B.
그래서, 예를 들어, 제 행렬이 2 3 4이고
So that, for example, if my matrix was two three four
또 다른 열이 있다고 해보면, 예를 들어 7 8 9이고,
and then had another column, say, seven eight nine,
여기 제 행렬이 — 예를 들어, 1 6으로 시작해서
and my matrix here has -- say, started with one six and then
또 다른 열이 0 0이라면, 그럼 —
had another column like zero zero, then --
여기 네 번째 방법이 있어요, 좋아요? 거기에 두 개의 열이 있고, 거기에 두 개의 행이 있어요.
here's the fourth way, okay? I've got two columns there, I've got two rows there.
그래서 아름다운 규칙은 — 열과 행으로 전체를 보면
So the beautiful rule is -- see, the whole thing by columns and rows
제가 첫 번째 열을 첫 번째 행으로 곱하고
is that I can take the first column times the first row
두 번째 열을 두 번째 행으로 곱해서 더할 수 있다는 거예요.
So that's the fourth way -- that I can take columns times rows,
첫 번째 열 곱하기 첫 번째 행, 두 번째 열 곱하기 두 번째 행을 더하는 거예요. 사실, 제가 뭘 얻을까요?
first column times first row, second column times second row and add. Actually, what will I get?
그 행렬 곱셈의 답이 뭐가 될까요?
What will the answer be for that matrix multiplication?
음, 이건 그냥 0을 주니까, 사실 저는 다시 이거 — 그게 답이에요,
Well, this one it's just going to give us zero, so in fact I'm back to this -- that's the answer,
그 행렬 곱셈에 대한 거예요. 저는 여기 행렬 곱셈에 대한 이 사실들을 올려놓는 게 기뻐요.
for that matrix multiplication. I'm happy to put up here these facts about matrix
왜냐하면 그건 저에게 이런 특별한 행렬들을 적을 기회를 주니까요.
multiplication, because it gives me a chance to write down special matrices like this.
이건 특별한 행렬이에요. 그 모든 행들이 같은 선 위에 있어요.
This is a special matrix. All those rows lie on the same line.
그 모든 행들이 1 6을 지나는 선 위에 있어요. 제가 이 모든 행 벡터들을 그림으로 그리면,
All those rows lie on the line through one six. If I draw a picture of all these row vectors,
그건 모두 같은 방향이에요. 제가 이 두 개의 열 벡터들을 그림으로 그리면,
they're all the same direction. If I draw a picture of these two column vectors,
그건 같은 방향에 있어요. 나중에 저는 이런 언어를 사용할 거예요.
they're in the same direction. Later, I would use this language.
너무 나중도 아니에요. 저는 행 공간(row space)이, 행들의 모든 조합 같은 거라고 말할 거예요.
Not too much later, either. I would say the row space, which is like all the combinations of the rows,
이 행렬에 대해선 그냥 선이에요. 행 공간은 벡터 1 6을 지나는 선이에요.
is just a line for this matrix. The row space is the line through the vector one six.
모든 행들이 그 선 위에 있어요. 그리고 열 공간(column space)도 선이에요.
All the rows lie on that line. And the column space is also a line.
모든 열들이 벡터 2 3 4를 지나는 선 위에 있어요.
All the columns lie on the line through the vector two three four.
그래서 이건 정말 최소한의 행렬 같아요. 그리고 그건 이 1들 때문이에요.
So this is like a really minimal matrix. And it's because of these ones.
좋아요. 그럼 그게 세 번째 방법이에요.
Okay. So that's a third way.
이제 저는 행렬 곱셈에 대해 한 가지 더 말하고 싶어요, 이 주제에 있는 동안에요.
Now I want to say one more thing about matrix multiplication while we're on the subject.
그건 이거예요. 여러분은 또한 행렬을 블록(block)으로 나눠서
And it's this. You could also multiply -- You could also cut the matrix into blocks
곱셈을 할 수도 있어요. 그게 정말 너무 유용해서 언급하고 싶어요.
and do the multiplication by blocks. Yet that's actually so, useful that I want to mention it.
블록 곱셈(block multiplication)이요. 그래서 저는 제 행렬 A를 가지고, 그걸 쪼갤 수 있어요, 예를 들어,
Block multiplication. So I could take my matrix A and I could chop it up, like,
단순하게 하기 위해, 네 개의 정사각 블록으로 쪼개볼게요.
maybe just for simplicity, let me chop it into two -- into four square blocks.
정사각 행렬이라고 가정해 볼게요. 좋은 경우를 취해볼게요. 그리고 B도 정사각이고, 같은 크기라고 해볼게요.
Suppose it's square. Let's just take a nice case. And B, suppose it's square also, same size.
그래서 이 크기들이 꼭 같을 필요는 없어요.
So these sizes don't have to be the same.
그들이 해야 하는 건 제대로 맞는 거예요. 여기선 확실히 맞을 거예요.
What they have to do is match properly. Here they certainly will match.
자, 여기 블록 곱셈의 규칙이 있어요. 만약 이게 A1, A2, A3, A4 같은 블록들을 가지고 있다면,
So here's the rule for block multiplication, that if this has blocks like, A --
여기 블록들이요, 그리고 이 블록들이 B1, B2, B3, B4라면요? 그럼 저는 답을 블록으로 찾을 수 있어요.
so maybe A1, A2, A3, A4 are the blocks here,
그리고 여러분이 저에게 그 블록에 뭐가 들어가는지 말해 준다면, 그럼 저는 오늘 나머지 시간 동안 행렬 곱셈에 대해 조용히 있을게요.
and these blocks are B1, B2,3 and B4? Then the answer I can find block.
그 블록에 뭐가 들어가나요? 보세요, 이건 — 이 행렬은 —
And if you tell me what's in that block, then I'm going to be quiet about matrix multiplication for the rest of the day.
이 행렬들은, 예를 들어, 20행 20열일 수 있고, 블록들이 10행 10열일 수 있어요. 모든 블록이
What goes into that block? You see, these might be -- this matrix might be --
같은 모양인 쉬운 경우를 취해보면요. 요점은 제가 그걸 블록으로 곱할 수 있다는 거예요.
these matrices might be, like, twenty by twenty with blocks that are ten by ten, to take the easy case where all the blocks
그리고 여기 뭐가 들어가나요? 답에서 그 블록이 뭐죠?
are the same shape. And the point is that I could multiply those by blocks.
A1 B1이요, 그건 행렬 곱하기 행렬이고, 크기가 맞아요, 10행 10열이죠.
And what goes in here? What's that block in the answer?
더 있나요? 더해서, 거기에 뭐가 더 들어가나요?
A1 B1, that's a matrix times a matrix, it's the right size, ten by ten.
A2 B3죠, 맞죠? 그건 그냥 블록 행 곱하기 블록 열 같아요.
Any more? Plus, what else goes in there?
아무도, 제 생각엔, 가우스(Gauss)조차도 그게 작동하는 걸 바로 보지 못했을 거예요.
A2 B3, right? It's just like block rows times block columns.
하지만 어떻게든, 우리가 그걸 확인해 보면, 다섯 가지 방법 모두 같은 곱셈을 하고 있어요.
Nobody, I think, not even Gauss could see instantly that it works.
그래서 이 익숙한 곱셈은 우리가 열로, 행으로, 열 곱하기 행으로, 그리고 블록으로 할 때
But somehow, if we check it through, all five ways we're doing the same multiplications.
정말 하고 있는 거예요.
So this familiar multiplication is what we're really doing when we do it
좋아요. 저는 그냥 행렬 곱셈에 대한 규칙을 명확히 해야겠어요.
by columns, by rows by columns times rows and by blocks.
좋아요.
Okay. I just have to, like, get the rules straight for matrix multiplication.
자, 저는 두 번째 주제인 역행렬(inverses)에 대해 준비됐어요. 좋아요.
Okay.
역행렬에 대해 준비됐어요.
All right, I'm ready for the second topic, which is inverses. Okay.
그리고 먼저 정사각 행렬(square matrices)에 대해 해볼게요.
Ready for inverses.
좋아요. 그래서 제가 정사각 행렬 A를 가지고 있어요.
And let me do it for square matrices first.
그리고 그건 역행렬이 있을 수도 있고 없을 수도 있죠, 맞죠? 모든 행렬이 역행렬을 가지는 건 아니에요. 사실, 그게 여러분이 행렬에 대해 물을 수 있는 가장 중요한 질문이에요.
Okay. So I've got a square matrix A.
만약 그게 정사각 행렬이라면, 그게 가역적인지(invertible) 아닌지예요?
And it may or may not have an inverse, right? Not all matrices have inverses. In fact, that's the most important question you can ask
만약 가역적이라면, 어떤 다른 행렬이 있어요. 그걸 A의 역행렬(A inverse)이라고 불러볼까요?
about the matrix, is if it's -- if you know it's square, is it invertible or not?
그리고 — 만약 A의 역행렬이 존재한다면 —
If it is invertible, then there is some other matrix, shall I call it A inverse?
여기 큰 "만약"이 있어요. 이 행렬이 존재한다면, 그리고 그게 언제 존재하는지 알아내는 게 정말 핵심이 될 거예요.
And what's the -- if A inverse exists --
그리고 만약 존재한다면, 그걸 어떻게 찾을까요?
there's a big "if" here. If this matrix exists, and it'll be really central to figure out
하지만 여기 제가 아직 — 끝내지 않은 방정식이 뭐죠?
when does it exist? And then if it does exist, how would you find it?
이 행렬이, 만약 존재한다면 A를 곱해서, 제 생각엔 단위 행렬(identity)을 만들어내요.
that I have to finish now? This matrix, if it exists multiplies A and produces,
하지만 정사각 행렬의 진짜 역행렬은 오른쪽에도 있을 수 있어요
I think, the identity.
— 이건 사실이에요, 그건 —
But a real -- an inverse for a square matrix could be on the right as well
만약 제가 — 네, 사실 이건 —
-- this is true, too, that it's --
이건 증명하기 쉬운 게 아니지만, 작동해요.
if I have a -- yeah in fact, this is not -- this is probably the --
정사각 행렬의 왼쪽 역행렬(left inverse)은 오른쪽 역행렬(right inverse)이기도 해요.
this is something that's not easy to prove, but it works.
만약 제가 왼쪽에서 단위 행렬을 얻는 행렬을 찾을 수 있다면,
That a left -- square matrices, a left inverse is also a right
그럼 오른쪽에서도 그 행렬이 단위 행렬을 만들어내요.
inverse. If I can find a matrix on the left that gets the identity,
직사각 행렬(rectangular matrices)에선, 우리는 왼쪽 역행렬이 오른쪽 역행렬이 아닌 경우를 볼 거예요.
then also that matrix on the right will produce that identity. For rectangular matrices, we'll see a left inverse
사실, 모양 때문에 그럴 수 없죠. 하지만 정사각 행렬에선, 모양이 그걸 허용하고, A가 역행렬을 가지면 그렇게 돼요.
that isn't a right inverse. In fact, the shapes wouldn't allow it. But for square matrices, the shapes
좋아요, 그럼 몇 가지 경우를 볼까요 — 보자고요. 부정적으로 말하기 싫지만,
allow it and it happens, if A has an inverse.
역행렬이 없는 경우에 대해 이야기해 볼게요.
Okay, so give me some cases -- let's see. I hate to be negative here, but let's talk
이 행렬들은 가역적(invertible) 또는 비특이(non-singular)라고 불려요 —
Can I talk about the singular case?
특이(singular) 경우에 대해 이야기해도 될까요?
No inverse.
역행렬이 없어요.
All right. Best to start with an example.
좋아요. 예제부터 시작하는 게 가장 좋겠네요.
Tell me an example -- let's get an example up here. Let's make it two by two --
예제를 하나 말해 주세요 — 여기 예제를 올려놓겠습니다. 2행 2열(2 by 2)로 해볼게요 —
of a matrix that has not got an inverse. And let's see why.
역행렬이 없는 행렬의 예요. 그리고 그 이유를 알아봅시다.
Let me write one up. No inverse. Let's see why.
하나 써볼게요. 역행렬이 없어요. 그 이유를 봅시다.
Let me write up -- one three two six.
1 3 2 6이라고 써놓겠습니다.
Why does that matrix have no inverse?
왜 이 행렬에 역행렬이 없을까요?
You could answer that various ways.
여러 가지 방법으로 대답할 수 있어요.
Give me one reason.
한 가지 이유를 말해 주세요.
Well, you could -- if you know about determinants, which you're not supposed to, you could take its determinant
음, 여러분이 행렬식(determinant)에 대해 안다면 — 아직 모른다고 가정하지만 — 행렬식을 구해보면
and you would get -- Zero. Okay.
0이 나와요. 좋아요.
Now -- all right. Let me ask you other reasons.
자 — 좋아요. 다른 이유를 물어볼게요.
I mean, as for other reasons that that matrix isn't invertible.
제 말은, 이 행렬이 가역적이지 않은 다른 이유요.
Here, I could use what I'm saying here.
여기서 제가 말하는 걸 사용할 수 있어요.
Suppose A times other matrix gave the identity.
A가 다른 행렬을 곱해서 단위 행렬(identity)을 만든다고 가정해 봅시다.
Why is that not possible? Because -- oh, yeah --
그게 왜 불가능할까요? 왜냐하면 — 오, 맞아요 —
I'm thinking about columns here. If I multiply this matrix A by some other matrix, then the --
저는 여기서 열(column)에 대해 생각하고 있어요. 제가 이 행렬 A를 어떤 다른 행렬로 곱하면 —
the result -- what can you tell me about the columns? They're all multiples of those columns, right?
결과는 — 열들에 대해 뭐라고 말할 수 있나요? 그건 모두 저 열들의 배수(multiple)이죠, 맞죠?
If I multiply A by another matrix that -- the product has columns that come from those columns.
제가 A를 다른 행렬로 곱하면 — 그 곱의 열들은 저 열들에서 오는 거예요.
So can I get the identity matrix? No way. The columns of the identity matrix, like one zero --
그럼 단위 행렬을 얻을 수 있을까요? 절대 안 돼요. 단위 행렬의 열들, 예를 들어 1 0은 —
it's not a combination of those columns, because those two columns lie on the -- both lie on the same line.
저 열들의 조합(combination)이 아니에요. 왜냐하면 저 두 열은 — 둘 다 같은 선 위에 있거든요.
Every combination is just going to be on that line and I can't get one zero.
모든 조합은 그 선 위에 있을 뿐이고, 1 0을 얻을 수 없어요.
So, do you see that sort of column picture of the matrix
그래서 행렬이 가역적이지 않다는 열 그림을 보시겠어요? 사실, 여기 또 다른 이유가 있어요. 이건 훨씬 더 중요한 이유예요.
Well, how can I say more important? All those are important. This is another way to see it.
음, 더 중요하다고 어떻게 말할 수 있냐고요? 다 중요해요. 이건 또 다른 보는 방법이에요.
A matrix has no inverse -- yeah -- here -- now this is important.
행렬에 역행렬이 없다 — 네 — 여기 — 이제 이건 중요해요.
A matrix has no -- a square matrix won't have an inverse if there's no inverse because I can solve --
행렬에 — 정사각 행렬(square matrix)에 역행렬이 없는 이유는 제가 풀 수 있기 때문이에요 —
I can find an X of -- a vector X with A times --
A 곱하기 X가 —
this A times X giving zero.
이 A 곱하기 X가 0을 주는 벡터 X를 찾을 수 있어요.
This is the reason I like best. That matrix won't have an inverse.
이게 제가 가장 좋아하는 이유예요. 그 행렬은 역행렬을 가질 수 없어요.
Can you -- well, let me change I to U.
혹시 — 음, I를 U로 바꿀게요.
So tell me a vector X that, solves A X equals zero.
그럼 A X = 0을 푸는 벡터 X를 말해 주세요.
I mean, this is, like, the key equation. In mathematics, all the key equations have zero on the right-hand side.
제 말은, 이건 핵심 방정식이에요. 수학에서 모든 핵심 방정식은 오른쪽이 0이죠.
So what's the X? Tell me an X here -- so now I'm going to put -- slip in the X that you tell me
그럼 X가 뭐예요? 여기 X를 말해 주세요 — 이제 여러분이 말해 주는 X를 넣어서
and I'm going to get zero. What X would do that job?
0을 얻을 거예요. 어떤 X가 그 역할을 할까요?
Three and negative one? Is that the one you picked, or -- yeah. Or another -- well, if you picked zero with zero,
3과 -1? 그걸 골랐나요, 아니면 — 네. 아니면 또 다른 — 음, 만약 0과 0을 골랐다면,
I'm not so excited, right? Because that would always work. So it's really the fact that this vector
별로 흥분되지 않죠, 맞죠? 왜냐하면 그건 항상 되니까요. 그래서 정말 중요한 건 이 벡터가
isn't zero that's important. It's a non-zero vector and three negative one would do it.
0이 아니라는 거예요. 0이 아닌 벡터이고, 3 -1이 그걸 해내죠.
That just says three of this column minus one of that column is the zero column.
그건 이 열의 3배에서 저 열의 1배를 빼면 0 열이 된다는 거예요.
Okay. So now I know that A couldn't be invertible.
좋아요. 그럼 이제 A가 가역적일 수 없다는 걸 알았어요.
But what's the reasoning? If A X is zero, suppose I multiplied by A inverse.
하지만 그 추론이 뭐죠? 만약 A X가 0이라면, 제가 A의 역행렬로 곱한다고 가정해 봅시다.
Yeah, well here's the reason. Here -- this is why this spells disaster for an inverse.
네, 여기 이유가 있어요. 여기 — 이게 역행렬에 재앙을 부르는 이유예요.
The matrix can't have an inverse if some combination of the columns gives z- it gives nothing.
행렬은 열들의 어떤 조합이 0을 주면 — 아무것도 주지 않으면 역행렬을 가질 수 없어요.
Because, I could take A X equals zero, I could multiply by A inverse and what would I discover?
왜냐하면, 제가 A X = 0을 가지고, A의 역행렬로 곱하면 뭐를 발견할까요?
Suppose I take that equation and I multiply by -- if A inverse existed, which of course I'm going to come
제가 그 방정식을 가지고 — 만약 A의 역행렬이 존재한다고 가정하면, 물론 저는 그게 불가능하다는 결론에 이를 거지만,
to the conclusion it can't because if it existed, if there was an A inverse to this dopey matrix,
만약 이 멍청한 행렬에 A의 역행렬이 존재한다면,
I would multiply that equation by that inverse and I would discover X is zero.
저는 그 방정식을 그 역행렬로 곱해서 X가 0이라는 걸 발견할 거예요.
If I multiply A by A inverse on the left, I get X. If I multiply by A inverse on the right, I get zero.
왼쪽에서 A와 A의 역행렬을 곱하면 X가 나와요. 오른쪽에서 A의 역행렬로 곱하면 0이 나와요.
So I would discover X was zero. But it -- X is not zero. X -- this guy wasn't zero.
그래서 X가 0이라는 걸 발견할 거예요. 하지만 — X는 0이 아니에요. 이 녀석은 0이 아니었죠.
There it is. It's three minus one. So, conclusion -- only, it takes us some time to really work
그게 다예요. 3 -1이에요. 그래서 결론은 — 그 결론을 정말 다루는 데 시간이 좀 걸리지만 — 우리의 결론은 가역적이지 않은 행렬,
with that conclusion -- our conclusion will be that non-invertible matrices,
특이 행렬(singular matrices)은 그 열들의 어떤 조합이
singular matrices, some combinations of their columns
0 열을 준다는 거예요. 그들은 어떤 벡터 X를 0으로 보내버려요.
gives the zero column. They they take some vector X into zero.
그리고 A의 역행렬이 회복할 방법이 없죠, 맞죠? 그게 이 방정식이 말하는 거예요.
And there's no way A inverse can recover, right? That's what this equation says.
이 방정식은 제가 이 벡터 X를 가지고 A로 곱하면 0이 나온다고 말해요.
This equation says I take this vector X and multiplying by A gives zero.
하지만 그 다음에 A의 역행렬로 곱하면, 저는 0에서 절대 벗어날 수 없어요.
But then when I multiply by A inverse, I can never escape from zero.
그래서 A의 역행렬이 있을 수 없어요. 여기서 — 좋아요, 이제 고쳐서 —
So there couldn't be an A inverse. Where here -- okay, now fix --
좋아요. 이제 긍정적인 면으로 돌아가 봅시다.
all right. Now let me take -- all right, back to the positive side.
역행렬이 있는 행렬을 가져가 봅시다. 왜 그걸 뒤집지 않겠어요?
Let's take a matrix that does have an inverse. And why not invert it?
좋아요. 제가 — 그래서 이 세 번째 칠판에 행렬을 가져갈게요 — 좀 고칠까요?
Okay. Can I -- so let me take on this third board a matrix -- shall I fix that up a little?
역행렬이 있는 행렬을 말해 주세요.
Tell me a matrix that has got an inverse.
음, 제가 1 3 2 — 거기에 뭐를 넣을까요?
Well, let me say one three two -- what shall I put there?
음, 6은 넣지 말아야겠죠 — 맞죠?
Well, don't put six, I guess is -- right?
여기서 제가 좋아하는 숫자 있나요?
Do I any favorites here?
1? 아니면 8?
One? Or eight?
상관없어요. 뭐, 7? 7이요. 좋아요. 7은 행운의 숫자예요. 좋아요, 7, 좋아요.
I don't care. What, seven? Seven. Okay. Seven is a lucky number. All right, seven, okay.
좋아요. 그럼 — 이제 우리의 생각이 뭐죠? 우리는 이 행렬이 가역적이라고 믿어요.
Okay. So -- now what's our idea? We believe that this matrix is invertible. Those who like determinants have quickly taken its determinant
행렬식을 좋아하는 사람들은 빨리 행렬식을 구해서 0이 아니라는 걸 알아냈어요.
and found it wasn't zero. Those who like columns, and probably that --
열을 좋아하는 사람들은 — 아마 그 부서는 아직 완전히 인기 있진 않지만 — 저 두 열을 보고
that department is not totally popular yet -- but those who like columns will look at those two columns
이렇게 말하겠죠, "이봐, 저 열들은 다른 방향을 가리키고 있어. 그래서 뭐든지 얻을 수 있어."
and say, hey, they point in different directions. So I can get anything.
자, 제가 무슨 뜻인지 봅시다. A의 역행렬을 어떻게 계산할까요? 그래서 A의 역행렬 —
Now, let me see, what do I mean? How I going to computer A inverse? So A inverse --
여기 A의 역행렬이 있고, 이제 그걸 찾아야 해요. 그리고 이 곱셈을 하면 뭐가 나와요?
here's A inverse, now, and I have to find it. And what do I get when I do this multiplication?
단위 행렬이요.
The identity.
아시다시피, 2행 2열을 사용하는 걸 용서해 주세요. 하지만 — 계산을 관리하기 쉽게 하고 아이디어가 드러나게 하는 게 좋아요.
You know, forgive me for taking two by two-s, but -- lt's good to keep the computations manageable and let
좋아요, 이제 제가 원하는 아이디어가 뭐죠?
the ideas come out. Okay, now what's the idea I want?
저는 이 행렬 A의 역행렬을 찾고 있어요. 어떻게 찾을까요? 지금 저는 네 개의 숫자를 찾아야 해요.
I'm looking for this matrix A inverse, how I going to find it? Right now, I've got four numbers to find.
첫 번째 열을 볼게요.
I'm going to look at the first column.
이 첫 번째 열을 가져가 봅시다, A B. 거기에 뭐가 있죠?
Let me take this first column, A B. What's up there?
뭐 — 이걸 말해 주세요. 첫 번째 열은 어떤 방정식을 만족하나요?
What -- tell me this. What equation does the first column satisfy?
첫 번째 열은 A 곱하기 그 열이 1 0을 만족해요.
The first column satisfies A times that column is one zero.
답의 첫 번째 열이요. 그리고 두 번째 열, C D는 A 곱하기
The first column of the answer. And the second column, C D, satisfies A times
그 두 번째 열이 0 1을 만족해요.
that second column is zero one. You see that finding the inverse is like solving two systems.
역행렬을 찾는 게 두 개의 시스템을 푸는 것 같다는 걸 아시겠죠?
One system, when the right-hand side is one zero -- I'm just going to split it into two pieces.
한 시스템은 오른쪽이 1 0일 때 — 저는 그냥 두 조각으로 나눌게요.
I don't even need to rewrite it. I can take A times -- so let me put it here.
다시 쓸 필요도 없어요. A 곱하기 — 여기 놓겠습니다.
A times column j of A inverse is column j of the identity.
A 곱하기 A의 역행렬의 j번째 열은 단위 행렬의 j번째 열이에요.
I've got n equations. I've got, well, two in this case.
n개의 방정식이 있어요. 이 경우엔 두 개죠.
And they have the same matrix, A, but they have different right-hand sides. The right-hand sides are just the columns
그리고 같은 행렬 A를 가지지만, 오른쪽이 달라요. 오른쪽은 그냥 단위 행렬의 열들이에요, 이 녀석과 이 녀석.
of the identity, this guy and this guy. And these are the two solutions. Do you see what I'm going --
그리고 이게 두 개의 해예요. 제가 뭘 하려는지 아시겠죠 —
I'm looking at that equation by columns.
저는 그 방정식을 열 단위로 보고 있어요.
I'm looking at A times this column, giving that guy, and A times that column giving that guy. So -- Essentially -- so this is like the Gauss --
A 곱하기 이 열이 저 녀석을 주고, A 곱하기 저 열이 저 녀석을 주는 거예요. 그래서 — 본질적으로 — 이건 가우스(Gauss) 같은 —
we're back to Gauss. We're back to solving systems of equations, but we're solving --
다시 가우스로 돌아왔어요. 방정식 시스템을 푸는 거로 돌아왔지만, 우리는 —
we've got two right-hand sides instead of one. That's where Jordan comes in.
오른쪽이 하나가 아니라 두 개예요. 여기서 조던(Jordan)이 등장해요.
So at the very beginning of the lecture, I mentioned Gauss-Jordan, let me write it up again.
그래서 강의 처음에 제가 가우스-조던(Gauss-Jordan)을 언급했었죠. 다시 써놓겠습니다.
Okay. Here's the Gauss-Jordan idea.
좋아요. 여기 가우스-조던 아이디어가 있어요.
Gauss-Jordan solve two equations at once.
가우스-조던은 두 방정식을 동시에 풀어요.
Okay. Let me show you how the mechanics go.
좋아요. 그 메커니즘이 어떻게 되는지 보여줄게요.
How do I solve a single equation?
단일 방정식은 어떻게 푸나요?
So the two equations are one three two seven,
그래서 두 방정식은 1 3 2 7,
multiplying A B gives one zero.
A B를 곱하면 1 0이 나와요.
And the other equation is the same one three two seven multiplying C D gives zero one.
그리고 다른 방정식은 같은 1 3 2 7이 C D를 곱하면 0 1이 나와요.
Okay. That'll tell me the two columns of the inverse.
좋아요. 그게 저에게 역행렬의 두 열을 말해 줄 거예요.
I'll have inverse. In other words, if I can solve with this matrix A,
역행렬을 갖게 될 거예요. 다시 말해, 제가 이 행렬 A로 풀 수 있다면,
if I can solve with that right-hand side and that right-hand side, I'm invertible.
이 오른쪽과 저 오른쪽으로 풀 수 있다면, 저는 가역적이예요.
I've got it. Okay. And Jordan sort of said to Gauss, solve them together,
알겠어요. 그리고 조던은 가우스에게 이렇게 말했죠, "함께 풀어,
look at the matrix -- if we just solve this one, I would look at one three two seven,
행렬을 봐 — 우리가 이 하나만 푼다면, 저는 1 3 2 7을 보고,
and how do I deal with the right-hand side? I stick it on as an extra column, right?
오른쪽은 어떻게 다룰까요? 추가 열로 붙이죠, 맞죠?
That's this augmented matrix. That's the matrix when I'm watching the right-hand side
그래서 저는 그걸 추가 열로 그냥 따라가게 해요.
at the same time, doing the same thing to the right side that I do to the left? So I just carry it along as an extra column.
이제 저는 두 개의 추가 열을 따라갈 거예요.
Now I'm going to carry along two extra columns.
그리고 가우스가 원하는 대로 할 거예요, 맞죠? 소거법(elimination)을 할 거예요.
And I'm going to do whatever Gauss wants, right? I'm going to do elimination.
이걸 단순하게 만들고 이게 역행렬로 바뀔 거예요.
I'm going to get this to be simple and this thing will turn into the inverse.
이게 앞으로 나올 거예요. 저는 소거 단계를 해서 이걸
This is what's coming. I'm going to do elimination steps to make this
단위 행렬로 만들 거고, 그러면 놀랍게도 역행렬이 여기 나타날 거예요.
into the identity, and lo and behold, the inverse will show up here.
좋아요 — 해봅시다. 좋아요. 그럼 소거 단계가 뭐죠?
K--- let's do it. Okay. So what are the elimination steps?
보세요 — 여기 제 행렬 A가 있고, 단위 행렬이 붙어 있어요, 첨가된 거죠.
So you see -- here's my matrix A and here's the identity, like, stuck on, augmented on.
학생: 죄송한데... 스트랭: 네? 학생: — 2와 3이 바뀌어야 하는 거 아닌가요?
STUDENT: I'm sorry... STRANG: Yeah? STUDENT: -- is the two and the three supposed to be switched?
스트랭: 제가 — 오, 아니요, 바뀌어야 하는 게 아니었어요. 미안해요. 감사합니다.
STRANG: Did I -- oh, no, they weren't supposed to be switched. Sorry. Thanks.
좋아요. 정말 감사합니다. 그리고 — 제가 제대로 썼어요.
Okay. Thank you very much. And there -- I've got them right.
좋아요, 감사합니다. 좋아요.
Okay, thanks. Okay.
그럼 소거를 해봅시다. 좋아요, 간단할 거예요, 맞죠? 저는 이 행의 2배를 이 행에서 빼요.
So let's do elimination. All right, it's going to be simple, right? So I take two of this row away from this row.
그래서 이 행은 그대로 있고, 이거 2배를 여기서 빼요. 그러면 0과 1이 남고, 이거 2배를 여기서 빼면
So this row stays the same and two of those come away from this. That leaves me with a zero and a one and two of these away from
여러분이 얻는 게 이거죠 — 한 번의 소거 단계 후에 —
this is that what you're getting -- after one elimination step --
왼쪽 절반과 오른쪽 절반을 좀 나누겠습니다.
Let me sort of separate the -- the left half from the right half.
첫 번째 행의 2배가 두 번째 행에서 빼졌어요. 이제 이건 상삼각형(upper triangular form)이에요.
So two of that first row got subtracted from the second row. Now this is an upper triangular form.
가우스는 여기서 멈추겠지만, 조던은 계속하라고 해요. 위로 소거를 사용해요.
Gauss would quit, but Jordan says keeps going. Use elimination upwards.
방정식 2의 배수를 방정식 1에서 빼서 3을 없애요.
Subtract a multiple of equation two from equation one to get rid of the three.
그럼 끝까지 가봅시다. 이제 저는 — 이 녀석은 괜찮지만, 저는 —
So let's go the whole way. So now I'm going to -- this guy is fine, but I'm going to --
이제 뭐를 하나요? 역행렬을 만드는 마지막 단계가 뭐죠?
what do I do now? What's my final step that produces the inverse?
이걸 적당한 숫자로 곱해서 저기 위로 올려서 3을 없애요.
I multiply this by the right number to get up to ther to remove that three.
그래서 제가 — 여기 1이 있으니까, 피벗(pivot)이 거기 있어요. 이걸 3으로 곱해서 저기서 빼면,
So I guess, I -- since this is a one, there's the pivot sitting there. I multiply it by three and subtract from that,
뭐가 나와요? 1 0이 나와요 — 오, 네, 그게 제 전체 요점이었어요. 이걸 3으로 곱해서 저기서 빼면,
so what do I get? I'll have one zero -- oh, yeah that was my whole point. I'll multiply this by three and subtract from that,
7이 나와요. 그리고 이걸 3으로 곱해서 저기서 빼면,
which will give me seven. And I multiply this by three and subtract from that,
-3이 나와요.
which gives me a minus three.
그리고 제 희망, 믿음이 뭐죠?
And what's my hope, belief?
여기 A와 단위 행렬로 시작해서, 단위 행렬과 누구로 끝났죠?
Here I started with A and the identity, and I ended up with the identity and who?
그게 A의 역행렬이어야 해요.
That better be A inverse.
그게 가우스-조던 아이디어야요. 이 긴 행렬, 두 배 길이의 A I로 시작해서, 소거하고,
That's the Gauss Jordan idea. Start with this long matrix, double-length A I, eliminate,
이 부분이 I로 줄어들 때까지 소거하면, 이건 — 어떤 이유로든 —
eliminate until this part is down to I, then this one will -- must be for some reason,
그리고 그 이유를 찾아야 해요 — A의 역행렬이어야 해요. 그게 맞는지 확인해 볼까요?
and we've got to find the reason -- must be A inverse. Shall I just check that it works?
확인해 봅시다 — 이 부분을 이 행렬로 곱할게요.
Let me just check that -- can I multiply this matrix this part
A를 여기로 가져와서 그냥 그 곱셈을 해볼게요.
times A, I'll carry A over here and just do that
옛날 방식으로 할게요. 7 - 6은 1이에요.
multiplication. You'll see I'll do it the old fashioned way. Seven minus six is a one.
21 - 21은 0이고, -2 + 2는 0이고, -6 + 7은 1이에요.
Twenty one minus twenty one is a zero, minus two plus two is a zero, minus six plus seven is a one.
확인했어요. 그게 역행렬이에요.
Check. So that is the inverse.
그게 가우스-조던 아이디어야요. 그래서 여러분은 — 수요일 숙제 문제 중 하나 이상이
That's the Gauss-Jordan idea. So, you'll -- one of the homework problems or more than
그 단계를 밟아보라고 할 거예요.
one for Wednesday will ask you to go through those steps.
가우스-조던을 몇 번 해봐야 한다고 생각해요, 하지만 저는 —
I think you just got to go through Gauss-Jordan a couple of times, but I --
네 — 그 메커니즘을 보기 위해서요.
yeah -- just to see the mechanics.
하지만 중요한 건, 왜 — 무슨 일이 일어났는지예요?
But the, important thing is, why -- is, like, what happened?
왜 우리가 — 왜 거기서 A의 역행렬을 얻었을까요? 그걸 여러분에게 물어볼게요.
Why did we -- why did we get A inverse there? Let me ask you that.
우리가 — 그래서 우리는 —
We got -- so we take --
행 축소(row reduction)를 하고, 이 긴 행렬 A I에서 소거를 해서 첫 번째 절반이
We do row reduction, we do elimination on this long matrix A I until the first half
그 다음 두 번째 절반이 A의 역행렬이 나와요. 음, 그걸 어떻게 볼까요?
Then a second half is A inverse. is up. Well, how do I see that?
여기 어떻게 봤는지 올려놓겠습니다. 그래서 여기 제 가우스-조던이 있고, 제가 뭔가를 하고 있어요.
Let me put up here how I see that. So here's my Gauss-Jordan thing, and I'm doing stuff to it.
그래서 저는 — 음, E가 많네요.
So I'm -- well, whole lot of E's.
그게 소거 행렬(elimination matrices)이라는 걸 기억하세요. 그건 — 그건 우리가 지난번에 알아낸 거예요.
Remember those are those elimination matrices. Those are the -- those are the things that we figured out last
네, 그게 소거 단계예요. 행렬 형태로요,
time. Yes, that's what an elimination step is it's in matrix form,
저는 어떤 E들로 곱하고 있어요. 그리고 결과는 — 음, 저는 여러 E들로 곱하고 있어요.
I'm multiplying by some Es. And the result -- well, so I'm multiplying by a whole bunch
그래서 저는 — 전체 행렬을 E라고 부를 수 있을까요?
of Es. So, I get a -- can I call the overall matrix E?
그게 소거 행렬이에요, 그 모든 작은 조각들의 곱이죠. 작은 조각들이 뭐냐고요?
That's the elimination matrix, the product of all those little pieces. What do I mean by little pieces?
음, 여기서 그걸 2배 빼는 소거 행렬이 있었어요.
Well, there was an elimination matrix that subtracted two of that away from that.
그 다음에 저기서 3배를 빼는 소거 행렬이 있었죠. 이 경우엔 그게 다였어요.
Then there was an elimination matrix that subtracted three of that away from that. I guess in this case, that was all.
그래서 이 경우엔 E가 두 개뿐이었어요. 이 단계를 하는 하나와 저 단계를 하는 하나,
So there were just two Es in this case, one that did this step and one that did this step
그리고 그 둘이 합쳐져서 두 단계를 다 하는 E를 줬어요.
and together they gave me an E that does both steps.
그리고 최종 결과는 여기서 I를 얻는 거였어요.
And the net result was to get an I here.
그게 뭐여야 하는지 여러분이 말해 줄 수 있어요.
And you can tell me what that has to be.
이건 무슨 일이 일어났는지에 대한 그림 같아요. 만약 E가 A를 곱한다면, 그 E가 뭐든 간에 —
This is, like, the picture of what happened. If E multiplied A, whatever that E is --
우리는 이런 식으로 알아내진 않았어요.
we never figured it out in this way.
하지만 그 E가 뭐든, E 곱하기 A는 —
But whatever that E times that E is, E times A is --
E 곱하기 A가 뭐죠?
What's E times A?
I예요. 그 E가 뭐였든 간에, A를 곱해서 I를 만들어냈어요.
It's I. That E, whatever the heck it was, multiplied A and produced
그래서 E는 — E A = I는 E가 뭔지 말해 주죠, 즉 —
So E must be -- E A equaling I tells us what E is, I. namely it is --
학생: A의 역행렬이에요. 스트랭: A의 역행렬이에요. 훌륭해요.
STUDENT: It's the inverse of A. STRANG: It's the inverse of A. Great.
그리고 따라서, 두 번째 절반에서, E가 I를 곱하면, 그건 E —
And therefore, when the second half, when E multiplies I, it's E --
이걸 A의 역행렬이라고 놓아요. 이런 식으로 보는 그림이 보이세요?
Put this A inverse. You see the picture looking that way?
E 곱하기 A는 단위 행렬이에요. 그건 E가 뭔지 말해 주죠.
E times A is the identity. It tells us what E has to be.
역행렬이어야 해요, 그래서 오른쪽에서, 우리가 단위 행렬을 똑똑하게 붙였던 곳에서,
It has to be the inverse, and therefore, on the right-hand side, where E -- where we just smartly tucked on the identity,
그건 단계별로 — A의 역행렬로 바뀌고 있어요.
it's turning in, step by step -- It's turning into A inverse.
그게 가우스-조던 소거법의 설명이에요.
There is the statement of Gauss-Jordan elimination.
그게 역행렬을 찾는 방법이에요. 소거법으로 볼 수도 있고,
That's how you find the inverse. Where we can look at it as elimination,
n개의 방정식을 동시에 푸는 걸로 볼 수도 있고 —
as solving n equations at the same time -- --
n개의 열을 붙여서, 그 방정식들을 풀고, A의 역행렬의 n개의 열이 나와요.
and tacking on n columns, solving those equations and up goes the n columns of A inverse Okay, thanks.
좋아요, 감사합니다. 수요일에 뵙겠습니다.